Guide to the Plácido Vega Papers, 1855-1864
Department of Special Collections
Plácido Vega Papers,
1855-1864
Special Collections M0098
Vega, Plácido.
5.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of August Berner, 1915.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of documents (passports, invoices, inventories, financial statements certificates, records of judicial, legislative, and military proceedings, proclamations, etc.) and correspondence pertaining to the administration of Placido Vega as civil governor of the state of Sinaloa, Mexico, and as chief of the western division of the Liberation Army during the War of the Reform (1858-1860), and later, after 1862, as commander of the force from Sinaloa aiding the national government in resisting the French, in months following the French invasion at Veracruz.
This collection of papers, extending over a ten-year period from October, 1855, to November, 1864, gives insight into the progress of political and military affairs in Sinaloa and the northern states in particular, and in Mexico in general, during these years. The letters and documents of the collection, which concern both political and military matters, reflect the working of local and national politics, the development of personal animosities and intrigues, and the various difficulties of many natures which beset the national government, especially during the term of Benito Juarez as President of Mexico, after 1857.
The correspondence, often mingling the personal with matters of political or military interest, consists of
Letters written to Placido Vega (occasionally to other officials) by correspondents falling, for the most part, into the following categories:
Military officers under Placido Vega.
Military officers in charge of divisions of the army in other parts of Mexico, especially in the South (Many of these include Mexicans who figured prominently in national history, among them Generals Zuloaga, Zaragoza, Zarco, Jesus González Ortega, and Porfirio Díaz).
Local officials of civil government, including employees of Prefectures.
National political figures, among them many of prominence, such as Juarez, Comonfort, Lerdo de Tejada, and Doblado.
Diplomatic and consular officials, including representatives of Mexico abroad and representatives of foreign nations in Mexico.
Governors of other States of Mexico (Pesquiera, Sonora; Patoni, Durango; Gomez, Colima; Ogazon, Jalisco, etc.).
Customs officials.
Captains of foreign vessels, and owners of these ships.
Representatives of foreign businesses.
Relatives.
Copies of letters, many of them replies, sent by Plácido Vega to others.
Correspondence extends from November, 1855 into November, 1864. Correspondence is scanty from 1855 and the early months of 1856. From the years 1863 and 1864, there occur gaps in correspondence (which perhaps may be filled by the Bancroft collection, extending from 1863-1868). Letters written by Plácido Vega (copies) are lacking from the month of August, 1863, and from the months of January and April, 1864. The file also appears incomplete for the months of July, August, and November, 1864. The letters and documents of the collection present in special detail record of the uprising staged at Fuerte, in Sinaloa, by Remedios Meza and others in 1861 and the political conspiracy allegedly plotted and led against Plácido Vega by Ramón Corona in 1862 and 1863. Through the exchange of letters between Pesquiera and other officials in Sonora and Plácido Vega, considerable detail is recorded about efforts to suppress the Yaqui and Mayo Indian tribes in Sonora, while correspondence between Plácido vega and political figures, especially Juárez, at the capital and military officials in the South reflect the course of national developments, from events foreshadowing the French invasion, including the financial crisis of the Mexican government, to the landing of troops at Veracruz, the battle for Puebla, and the moving of the Federal government to new headquarters. In letters of 1863 appear first references to Plácido Vega's decision to go to San Francisco to procure arms and supplies for Mexican soldiers. Correspondence from 1864 includes letters written from Plácido Vega in San Francisco to supporters in Mexico, and from correspondents in Mexico to Vega in San Francisco (May, 1864, on).
Biographical Note
Plácido Vega
Organized opposition in Sinaloa in 1855 to the government of Santa Anna.
Served as Commander-in-Chief of Constitutional forces in Sonora and Sinaloa during the War of the Reform (1858-1860).
Served intermittently as governor of Sinaloa in the years 1859, 1860, 1861, 1862, and 1863, turning the office over successively to Francisco de P. Maldonado, Fortino León, Manuel Márquez, Fortino León, and Jesus García Morales, and A. Rosales.
After the invasion of Veracruz by the French in 1862, Plácido Vega sent men from the army in Sinaloa to the South in support of the Federal government, in its attempt to repel the French, and made a trip to the capital himself, stopping to converse with various officials along the way.
In the spring of 1864, with Jesus García Morales serving as governor of Sinaloa, Plácido Vega departed for San Francisco, California, to negotiate for arms and supplies for soldiers of the Mexican army.
Container List
- (October, 1855) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Passport issued in October, 1855, by Eustagio Buelna.
- (November, 1855) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Letter to Plácido Vega from Colonel Ramón Félix y Buelna concerning political appointment. Notes on official stationery from P. Valdez, officer of brigade of Sinaloa.
- (December, 1855) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Colonel J. J. Tostado concerning military matters; from Juan García; from Guillermo Vega; from Pomposo Verdugo, former governor of Sinaloa. Letter to Manuel Aragon, Colonel of Artillery, from Antonio Salarán; to P. Valdez from J. J. Tostado (military matters).
- (January, 1856) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Inventories; lists of supplies for Liberation Army of Sinaloa, and clothing distributed to company at Culiacán; official notes; letters to Plácido Vega from P. Valdez and others.
- (February, 1856) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Letter to Plácido Vega from Carlos Vega.
- (March, 1856) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Official notes; letters written to Plácido Vega by relatives and others.
- (April, 1856) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Correspondence: letters to Plácido Vega
  (C. Terrea, other)
- (June, 1856) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Letter to Plácido Vega from Felipe Cervantes.
- (July, 1856) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Letter to Plácido Vega from Mascinio Peiros (?)
- (August, 1856) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from M. de la Quintana and M. Granado.
- (October, 1856) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from José Vega, María Antonia Pacheco, Josefa Sarmiento, Castro de la Vega, Camilo Vega, Jesús Vega.
- (November, 1856) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  List of medicines acquired for army. Letters to Placido Vega from R. Félix y Buelna, Altagracia Vega, Carlos Vega, Camilo Vega, Jesús Vega, Joaquín Vega, Dr. Miglorio Crepet, others.
- (December, 1856) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Jesús Vega, Manuel Insunza, Félix Rojo, Refugio Ribera, Altagracia Vega, P. Blancarte, Francisco Gaxiola, R. Félix y Buelna, others. List of values of horses, etc.
- (January, 1857) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Rafael Urrea, Manuel Garibay, Mariano Delgado, Beatriz Vega, Carlos Vega, Francisco Vega, Jesús Vega, Tiburcio Vega, Franquelino Vega, Francisco Aragón, Manuel Sánchez Hildalgo, Jesús Gago, Josefa Sarmiento, others.
- (February, 1857) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Juan Medina, Trinidad Leíba, Jesús Vega, N. N., R. Félix y Buelna, Justo Quintero, Andrés Monzón, Juan López, José Silva, Miguel Vega, others.
- (March, 1857) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Justo Quintero, Andrés Monzón, Felipe Cervantes, Miguel Castro, Mariano Delgado, Jesús Vega (enclosing letter to latter from Luis Tirado); from Ignacio Rodríguez, Eduardo de la Vega, Jesús Gago, Eduardo Cárdenas, Jesús Esparragoza, Francisco Aragón, José Silva, Ignacio Gómez, Abelino Insunza, Miguel Insunza, others.
- (April, 1857) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Andrés Monzón, Justo Quintero, Hilario López, Jesús Gaxiola, Jorge de la Vega, Luis Tirado, Félix Rojo, Carlos Vega, Jesús Vega, Luis Antonio Vega, Manuel de la Vega, Ignacio González, Rafael Romero, Francisco Gutiérrez, Eduardo Cárdenas, Francisco Cárdenas, Agustín de Castro, José Orrantia, Buenaventura Insunza, Rosalio Garibay, Francisco Aragón, José Silva, others.
- (May, 1857) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Martín Guerrero, Francisco Gutiérrez, Joaquín Angulo, Rafael Romero, Jesús Villaseñor, Trinidad Leíba, Manuel de la Vega, Antonio Ramos, Manuel Hidalgo, Camilo Vega, Castro de la Vega, Manuel Romero, Félix Rojo, Beatriz Vega, Clara Luna, G. de la Vega, Luis Tirado, Andrés Monzón, Miguel Insunza, Abelino Insunza, others.
  Printed invitation to Plácido Vega from Office of Director of Public Education, requesting that Plácido Vega attend examination to be given on May 29, 1857.
- (June, 1857) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Justo Quintero, Eustagio Buelna, Félix Cañeda, M. Parrodi, Andrés Monzón, Trinidad Leíba, Jesús Vega, José de Cano, Francisco Alcalde.
- (July, 1857) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from M. Romero (concerning deputies to national congress), Pedro Bermúdez (concerning national congress), Manuel de la Vega, M. Salarán, Jorge de la Vega, M. Quintana, Miguel Salas, Antonio Rosales, José de Cano, Manuel Insunza, Miguel Insunza, F. de la Vega (financial), Beatriz de la Vega. Invoice (cigarette paper).
- (August, 1857) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Andrés Monzón, Justo Quintero, Agustín de Castro, T. de R. Torres, F. de la Vega, M. Romero, Felipe Escobar, Juan López, Tiburcio Vega, Francisco Gutiérrez, Buenaventura Insunza, P. Félix, Luis Tirado, Jorge de la Vega, Pomposo Verdugo. Financial statements sent Plácido Vega by Miguel Insunza, Eustagio Buelna, Fortunato de la Vega.
- (September, 1857) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from P. Ramos, Justo Quintero, Rafael Pomero, P. Félix, Francisco Belén Orrantia, Antonio Iriarte (?), Andrés Monzón, Beatriz de la Vega, Jose de R. Torres, Francisco Olantá, Jorge de la Vega, Manuel Insunza, Manuel Velásquez, Jesús Vega, Tiburcio de la Vega, Juan Carranza, others.
- (October, 1857) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Justo Quintero, Francisco Aragón, P. Félix, M. Romero, Gabriel Peña, F. Vega, M. Monzón, Juan Medina, Martín Guerrero, José Gimeno, G. G. Hidalgo, Antonio Iriarte (?), P. Romero, Juan Gutiérrez, Saturno Cárdenas, Jesús Vega, José M. Villarreal, Manuel Parrodi, M. Sánchez Hidalgo, Juan Gastelum, others.
- (November, 1857) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Josefa Sarmiento, M. Insunza, Guadalupe Fonseca, José Medina, F. de la Vega, José de R. Torres, Juan F. Gastelum, M. Romero, M. de la Quintana, Rosario Gastelum, Jesús Esparragosa, others.
- (December, 1957) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Rosario Gastelum, Justo Quintero, Martín Guerrero, Miguel Insunza, G. Fonseca, M. Sánchez Hidalgo, M. Félix, Andrés, Monzón, Antonio Ramos, J. de R. Torres, M. Salas, S. Cárdenas, Jesús Gago, José M. Bulnes, F. de la Vega.
- (January, 1858) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Official notes from P. Valdez; letters to Plácido Vega from José Yáñez, Altagracia Vega, Francisco Delgado, Guadalupe Gómez, G. Fonseca, Rosario Gastelum, Máximo Vega, Manuel Parrodi, F. de la Vega, Justo Quintero, M. Salas, A. Villarreal, M. Insunza, Tiburcio Vega, Francisco López, others. Financial statements from L. Ibarra, P. Félix.
- (February, 1858) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from G. de la Vega, Jesús Río, A. de Orrantia, General Ignacio Zaragoza? (journey to capital; reference to Juarez and political matters, to Plácido Vega's promotion in command); from Leoón Agulo, José González Echeverría, Ignacio Orozco, Fortino León (governmental matters), J. García Morales (governmental matters), A Villaverde (financial matters); from Prudencio Fel Ignacio Pesquiera, Jesús Vega, Antonio de la Vega, Francisco Ferrel, Carlos Rivas, M. Carreaga, L. Valdez, Francisco Cortés, Pedro Ogazón (reference to Miramón); from M. Zamacona (military matters); from R. Tobar, J. Río, M. Doblado, Emilio Lamberg, C. Peña, J. Gómez Flórez, others. Military notes from Jesús González Ortega (occupation of Veracruz).
- (February, 1958) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from A. Salas, G. Fonseca, C. Beltrán, P. Félix, M. Insunza, Ramón Ribera, Francisco Gutiérrez, A. Morales, Beatriz Vega, F. Gastelum, Manuel Parrodi, J. Guerrero, others.
- (March, 1858) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from G. de la Vega, R. Yáñez, L. Yáñez, J. de R. Torres, Manuel Parrodi, R. Gastelum, J.J. Medina, G. Guerrero, J. Trinidad, A. Iriarte (?), A. Ramos, A. Villarreal, F. Miranda, José de Cano, J. Esparragoza, J. Buelna, J. Alcalá, others.
- (April, 1858) (Box 2, Folder 29)
  29
  Letters to Plácido Vega from J. Ramos, A. de Castro, Jesus Vega, C. Beltrán, M. Salas, S. Cárdenas, G. Guerrero, others. Financial statement submitted by J. Gastelum.
- (May, 1858) (Box 2, Folder 30)
  30
  Letters to Plácido Vega from A. de la Vega (statement of expenditures included); from A. Ramos, M. Guerrero, E. Rodríguez, Trinidad Leíba, I. Guerrero, others.
- (June, 1858) (Box 2, Folder 31)
  31
  Letters to Plácido Vega from E. Lamberg (reference to defeat of Buelna and consequences); from A. Ramos, A. Iriarte (?).
- (October, 1858) (Box 2, Folder 32)
  32
  Letters to Plácido Vega from T. Lagarma, J. García Morales, Rafael Parras, Bulnes.
- (November, 1858) (Box 2, Folder 33)
  33
  Letters to Plácido Vega from P. Pinzón, P. Lagarma, F. Maldonado, Camilo de la Vega, Pablo Ribera, Pomposo Verdugo, Manuel Palomares, J. Esparragoza, A. Rosales (military matters: cavalry), others.
- (December, 1858) (Box 2, Folder 34)
  34
  Letters to Plácido Vega from J. García Morales, P. Lagarma, Agustín Hermosillo, Mariano Delgado, Pedro Pinzón, Quintin Douglas, M. Romero, Camilo Ibarra, Francisco M. de Avila, Pablo Ribera, Antonio Canalejo, Camilo Vega, A. Vega, others.
- (January, 1859) (Box 2, Folder 35)
  35
  Letters to Plácido Vega from R. Félix y Buelna, A. Rosales, T.M. Bulnes, S. Sánchez, Amado Blancarte, F. Merino, M. Romero, F. de P. Fernández, A. Hermosillo, José de R. Torres, José Padilla, Josefa Sarmiento, Ignacio de la Vega, Pablo Ribera, A. Canalejo, F. Maldonado, José M. Amador, Jesús Casteñada, others. Official document recording recommendations of officials of section of Constitutional Party meeting at Mazatlán in January, 1859.
- (February, 1859) (Box 2, Folder 36)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Luis Tirado, Calixto Peña, A. Palacio, F. Palacio, Camilo Vega, Mariano Romero, Francisca Mendasona, Martina de la Vega, Luis Villarreal, José M. Villarreal, Jesús Río, C. Torres, A. Haas (financial statement included); from A. Aldrete, Ignacio Graval, F. Tirado, Josefa Sarmiento, Ignacio Martínez Valenzuela, Crispín Palomares, Ramón Gutiérrez, Carlos de Ochoa, Juan Álvarez, others.
- (March, 1859) (Box 2, Folder 37)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from E. Maldonado, Arcadio Vega, A. Blancarte, J. J. Tostado, Calixto Peña, José de R. Torres, Camilo de la Vega, M. Romero, José Sánchez, Juan Ávilez, Castro de la Vega, A. Palacio, C. Isabal, A. Aldrete, L. Villarreal, C. Beltrán, Carlos Ochoa, F. Ortiz, J. Río, M. López, F. Andrade, J. Esparragoza (including list of expenses); from Manuel Fernández, Antonio Cabanilla, Valentino Vidaurrita, others.
- (April, 1859) (Box 2, Folder 38)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Manuel Garibay, J. Villarreal, Ignacio Graval, Manuel Parrodi, F. Orrantia, F. Ramos, P. Blancarte, R. Gutiérrez, G. Sarmiento, R. Maldonado, Sofía Calderón (verse: tribute to defenders of liberty); from Camilo Vega, Josefa Sarmiento, Camilo Ibarra, M. Romero, A. Blancarte, M. de la Quintana, A. Canalejo, others.
- (May, June, 1859) (Box 2, Folder 39)
  Copy of proclamation to inhabitants of Sinaloa issued by I. Pesquiera, as Provisional Governor (June, 1859). Letters to Plácido Vega from F. Tirado, A. Ramos, F. Aragón, R. Orrantia, M. Aragón, P. Mendoza, J. Villarreal, J. Guerrero, I. Graval, A. Palacio, others.
- (June, 1859) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Victoriano Morales, F. Ortiz, Manuel Garibay, Jesús Vega, F. Ferrel, M. Serrano, José Hilario López, B. Insunza, Carlos Vega, J. Esparragoza, others. List of funds acquired by governor for celebration of mass. List of expenses (sums owed for wages, etc.).
- (July, 1859) (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Ramón Corona, J. Carranza, Pedro Ogazón, Eduardo Norton, José Sánchez, Juan García, I. Pesquiera, Manuel Márquez, I. Valenzuela, Antonio Ochoa, P. Blancarte, Juan Valdez, José Sánchez, R. Félix y Buelna, Camilo Vega, M. Delgado, Carlos Ávilez, Miguel Urrea, Trinidad Leíba, Antonio de la Vega, P. Almada, Luis Tostado, A. Barreto, A. Posales, M. de la Quintana, Eduardo Cabrera, F. Castro, Carlos Vega, others. Copies of letters or portions of letters sent to Pesquiera by director of mint at Culiacán; copies on official stationery of letters from Pesquiera.
- (August, 1859) (Box 2, Folder 42)
  42
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Andrés Villaseñor, F. Cervantes, I. Graval, E. Félix, Juan Valdez, Camilo Vega, M. Delgado, C. Ibarra, M. Márquez, I. Pesquiera (affairs of state), Luis Tostado, M. Serrano, M. Parrodi, Miguel Montano, R. Corona, General Esteban Coronado (military matters, plans); from J. M. Patoni, P. Jaramillo, A. Barreto, C. Peña, P. Blancarte, Benito Juárez (state of affairs, plans); from M. Ocampo, Jesus Alvarez, P. Guerrero, E. Norton, R. Felix y Buelna, L. Ibarra, F. Tostado, Carlos Vega, A. Hermosillo, Rafael Casilla, others. Financial statement submitted by M. Urrea.
- (September, 1859) (Box 2, Folder 43)
  43
  Letters to Plácido Vega from General Coronado (military report: developments, plans); from Juan Sepúlveda, V. Morales, P. Almada, Juan Ávilez, Jose Arzapalo, F. Aragón, Manuel Perón, José Levada, C. Riberos, J. Sánchez, A. Martínez, Juan Carranza, José Rojo, Calixto Peña, Rafael Álvarez, Luis Tostado, L. Aguilar, I. Graval, F. Tirado, Carlos Vega, Jorge de la Vega, M. Quintero, José Pareja, A. Hermosillo, Jesús Vega, I. Orrantia, F. Chávez, Carlos Ávilez, R. Félix y Buelna (military developments), M. Delgado, José Castro, Camilo Vega, others. Lists of names of officers of battalion of Sinaloa.
- (October, 1859) (Box 2, Folder 44)
  44
  Letters to Plácido Vega from A. Ochoa, A. de Ia Vega, I. Graval, F. Alcalde, Rafael Álvarez, A. Canalejo, R. Corona, L. Tostado, F. Almada, Rafael Alvarado, Benito Juárez (affairs of state; conference with Eduardo Conner); from J. González Ortega; General Coronado (Preparation for combat near Guadalajara); from Pesquiera, Dr. J.M.Crepel (article from journal Le Trait D' Union telling of treatment for rabies included); from R. Félix y Buelna, M. Peiros, A. Hermosillo, J. Medina, others. Copies of letters sent by Plácido Vega to Pesquiera and General Coronado. Copy of letter sent to General Coronado by Pedro Ogazón (concerning advance upon Guadalajara; plans; statistics: size of force).
- (November, 1859) (Box 3, Folder 46)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Joaquín Mugarrieta, P. Ogazón(Military developments), I. Pesquiera (administrative matters), J.M. Patoni (political support), J. González Ortega (military developments in South), E. Norton (political appointments), Sidney Grenfell, Captain of English ship Amethyst; from others, including military officers and civil officials (employees of prefectures, customs officials, etc.).
- (December, 1859) (Box 3, Folder 47)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from P. Ogazón, military officers, customs officials; from Camilo Vega, J. M. Patoni (political, military matters); from I. Pesquiera. Outline of steps to be taken in campaign (December, 1859). Proclamation to inhabitants of District of Tepic issued by Commander Fernando García de la Cadena (November, 1859).
- (January, 1860) (Box 3, Folder 48)
  Letters to Plácido Vega (as governor of Sinaloa) from Mugarrieta, Pesquiera, Ramón Corona, Patoni (concerning levy imposed by General Coronado); from R. Félix y Buelna, M. Delgado, Antonio Vega; from employees of prefectures and customs officials; others.
- (February, 1860) (Box 3, Folder 49)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from military officers; from Mugarrieta, A. Vega, R. Meza (reference to affairs in Durango); from J. García Morales.
- (March, 1860) (Box 3, Folder 50)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from A. Blancarte, Jusús Vega, I. Pesquiera, Mugarrieta, John B. Weller (letter of introduction for Captain W. Twist); from military officers, local officials, others.
- (April, 1860) (Box 3, Folder 51)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from J. García Moral es, R. Félix y Buelna, A. Ochoa, E. Félix (including list of officers selected from company at Sinaloa in April, 1860); from Fortino León (payment of sums owed soldiers); from P. Ogazón, Dr. Crepel, R. Corona, M. Márquez, Mugarrieta, R. Meza, A. Vega, A. Rojas, others. Financial statement. Copy of letter sent to Colonel Antonio Rojas from R. Corona (instructions). Official notes; statements concerning march to San Blas.
- (May, 1860) (Box 3, Folder 52)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from E. Félix, R. Félix y Buelna, A. Rojas, Fortino León, M. Márquez, P. Ogazón, Carlos Norton (San Blas). Letters from Plácido Vega (copies) to Fortino León, M. Márquez, I. Banda, L. Tostado, P. Pinzón, A. Hermosillo, other military officers, supporters (instructions). Reports by military officers, other officials (San Blas and other matters). Proclamation to inhabitants of Sinaloa by Plácido Vega, announcing Fortino León as Provisional Governor.
- (June, 1860) (Box 3, Folder 53)
  Letters to Fortino León from military officers, others. Letters to Plácido Vega from Fortino León, R. Félix y Buelna (list of candidates for government positions in Sinaloa); from P. Ogazón, A. Rojas, others. Official statements and reports by P. Ogazón, treasurer, other officials.
- (July, 1860) (Box 3, Folder 54)
  Official records; statements by P. Ogazón regarding decisions made for re-establishment of tranquility in area; statements by R. Corona, others. Documents made out by P. Ogazón concerning release of prisoners; records of conduct of soldiers; of disorder; of action at Noria, near Mazatlán; of uprising staged by R. Meza. Papers made out in name of Urbano Gómez, governor of state of Colima, including proclamation declaring Gómez governor. Letters to Fortino León from A. Paredes, L. Tirado. Letters to Plácido Vega from A. Barreto. M. Romero, Ubano Gómez, I. Zaragoza, Fortino León, P. Ogazón, S. Aranda, E. Huerta (governor of Morelia), R. Corona, J. González Ortega, A. Herrera (instructions). Letters from Plácido Vega to S. Degollado, Fortino León, E. Huerta, G. Medina, head of division in Morelia; to M. Romero, Camilo Vega, E. Félix, M. Delgado, others.
- (August, 1860) (Box 3, Folder 55)
  Official records; statements by C. Peña, instructions to L. Tostado, etc. Letters to Plácido Vega from Urbano Gómez, J. Bulnes, E. Félix, M. Ramírez, M. Romero (concerning return of Comonfort), P. Ogazón, L. Tostado, others. Letter from Plácido Vega to P. Ogazón (Military matters).
- (September, 1860) (Box 4, Folder 56)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from F. Aragón, Bulnes, P. Verdugo, I. Pesquiera, A. de la Vega, F. Isabal (including financial statement), Luis Tostado, C. Peña, Camilo Vega, Jesús Vega, Buelna, others. Letters from Plácido Vega to Benito Juárez (state of affairs); to Juan Alvarez, Pesquiera, Antonio Vega, others.